Guide to the Frederic Goudy Papers, 1903-1966
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Frederic Goudy Papers
1903-1966
Goudy, Frederic W. (Frederic William), 1865-1947
6 cubic feet (14 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, articles by and about Goudy, type specimens, type and other printing hardware, memorabilia, and other materials relating to Frederic Goudy and his type designs.
Biographical Note
Frederic William Goudy was one of the foremost American typographers and printers of the twentieth century. Over the course of his long career, he designed dozens of typefaces—including Lanston, Kennerley, and Goudy Old Style—many of which are still used today. Goudy is also known for his work with the Village Press, which he founded in 1903 with an associate, William Ransom. After buying out Ransom, Goudy moved the press to a number of locations, eventually establishing it in 1920 at Deepdene, his home in Marlboro, New York. At Deepdene, Goudy and his wife, Bertha Sprinks Goudy (1869–1935), who worked as compositor, produced a wide range of books, pamphlets, broadsides, and ephemera. In 1924 the Goudys purchased the Albion printing press that had belonged to William Morris, founder of the Kelmscott Press. Goudy continued to use this press until 1939, when a fire destroyed his Deepdene workshop, forcing him to close the Village Press permanently. In addition to operating the Village Press, Goudy served as artistic director of the Lanston Monotype Machine Company, for which he designed many notable typefaces. He also lectured at several educational institutions, including Vassar College. Born on March 18, 1865, in Bloomington, Illinois, Frederic Goudy died on May 11, 1947, at his Deepdene home.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, articles by and about Goudy, type specimens, type and other printing hardware, memorabilia, and other materials relating to Frederic Goudy and his type designs.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Village Press Collection
Subject Headings
Names:
Borden, Fanny; Emmons, Earl H., 1888-; Goudy, Bertha, 1869-1935; Kennerley, Mitchell, 1878-1950; MacCracken, H. N. (Henry Noble), 1880-1970; Rogers, Bruce, 1870-1957
Organizations:
Lanston Monotype Machine Company; Maverick Press; Village Press
Subjects:
Printing--United States--History--Sources; Type and type-founding--United States--Specimens
Document Types:
Type (composition equipment); Type specimens
VCL Categories
Printing and Publishing
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl December, 2011. Updated by Mark Seidl January-March, June, 2014.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in ten series. See Series List below for arrangement within each series.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1923-1955; (Box 1)
  This series includes Goudy's correspondence with Fanny Borden, Alice Goudy Lochhead's correspondence with Fanny Borden, Goudy's correspondence with the Vassar College Library, correspondence relating to the Vassar College Village Press collection, and unidentified correspondence. Arranged chronologically.
- Series II. Essays and Addresses, circa 1933-circa 1941; (Boxes 1, 6, and 13)
  This series consists of Goudy's essays and addresses. Of particular interest are the addresses he delivered at Vassar College. Arranged chronologically.
- Series III. Publications, 1903-1960; (Boxes 1, 2, and 13)
  Divided into two subseries, this series consists of articles by and about Goudy. Each subseries is arranged chronologically.
- Series IV. Type and Type Specimens, circa 1923-1946; (Boxes 2, 6, 8, 9, and 14)
  This series includes type, quoins, and other printing hardware, as well as printed specimens and other materials relating to the typefaces Goudy designed. Arranged alphabetically.
- Series V. Broadsides, circa 1920-circa 1942; (Boxes 4, 6, 14, and 15)
  This series includes broadsides printed by the Village Press and Maverick Press, as well as unidentified broadsides. Arranged alphabetically.
- Series VI. Slides, After 1933; (Boxes 10-12)
  This series consists of photographic slides of examples of Goudy's typefaces, monograms, and other designs. Arranged numerically.
- Series VII. Book Covers, Bookplates, and Other Designs, 1910-circa 1946; (Boxes 2, 6, and 15)
  In this series are book covers, bookplates, brochures, pamphlets, title pages, and monograms designed by Goudy. Also included are examples of the masthead Goudy designed for Vassar College's Miscellany News. Arranged chronologically.
- Series VIII. Exhibits, Honors, and Tributes, 1923-1966; (Boxes 2, 3, 6, 13, and 14)
  This series includes materials relating to exhibits of Goudy's type faces and designs, as well as addresses, songs, and other materials produced in honor of him. Arranged alphabetically.
- Series IX. Portraits and Memorabilia, c. 1930-c. 1946; (Boxes 3, 4, 6, 7, 13, and 14)
  This series consists of photographs, portraits, and memorabilia. Of particular interest is a bas relief portrait of Frederic and Bertha Goudy. Arranged alphabetically.
- Series X. Miscellaneous Files, 1932-1957; (Boxes 4, 5, and 6)
  This series includes files relating to the death of Bertha Goudy and Goudy's Deepdene estate. Also included are materials pertaining to the Bruce Rogers Lectern Bible and to the Maverick Press. Arranged alphabetically.
Container List
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Letters to Fanny Borden, circa 1923-circa 1945 (Folder 1.1)
  - Alice Goudy Lochhead letters, circa 1939-1952 (Folder 1.2)
  - Vassar College Library to Frederic Goudy (copies), 1942-1943 (Folder 1.3)
  - Vassar College Library Correspondence re. Village Press Collection, 1927-1960 (Folder 1.4)
  - Unidentified Correspondence with Goudy, 1939, undated (Folder 1.5)
  - Unidentified Correspondence regarding Village Press, 1938 (Folder 1.6)
- Series II. Essays and Addresses
  - Addresses at Vassar College, circa 1933-circa 1940 (Folder 1.7)
  - The Design of Types, circa 1941 (Folder 6.1)
  - "Evening at Deepdene,", 1938 (Folder 6.2)
  - [Origin of the printer's mark], undated (Folder 1.8)
  - "The Type Speaks,", 1938 (Folder 1.9)
  - "The Type Speaks,", 1938; [oversize] (Folder 13.1)
- Series III. Publications
  - Articles by Goudy
    - 1921-1930 (Folder 1.10)
    - 1932-1936 (Folder 1.11)
    - 1937-1938 (Folder 1.12)
    - 1940-circa 1942 (Folder 1.13)
  - Articles about Goudy
    - 1919-1923 (Folder 1.14)
    - 1924-1929 (Folder 1.15)
    - 1932 (Folder 1.16)
    - 1933-1935 (Folder 1.17)
    - 1936-1937 (Folder 1.18)
    - 1938 (Folder 1.19)
    - 1939 (Folder 1.20)
    - 1940-1942 (Folder 1.21)
    - 1944-1945 (Folder 1.22)
    - 1930-1948 (Folder 13.2)
    - 1947-1948 (Folder 1.23)
    - 1953-1970 (Folder 2.1)
    - undated (Folder 2.2)
    - (minor mentions), circa 1920-1938 (Folder 2.3)
    - (minor mentions), 1939-1948 (Folder 2.4)
- Series IV. Type and Type Specimens
  - Assorted type and printing hardware, undated; [boxes are heavy] (Boxes 8-9)
  - "Californian,", circa 1940-circa 1941 (Folder 2.5)
  - "Collier Old Style,", 1923 (Folder 6.3)
  - "Deepdene,", 1935-1961 (Folder 2.6)
  - "Franciscan,", 1934, 1940 (Folder 2.7)
  - "Friar,", 1938 (Folder 2.8)
  - "Garamond,", 1928-1939 (Folder 2.9)
  - Goudy types, 1929-1938 (Folder 2.10)
  - Goudy types, 1941-1956; [includes "A record of Goudy type designs," compiled by Goudy] (Folder 2.11)
  - Goudy types, undated (Folder 2.12)
  - Goudy types, undated (Folder 6.4)
  - "Greek,", circa 1934 (Folder 2.13)
  - "Italian Old Style,", circa 1924-circa 1926 (Folder 2.14)
  - "Kaatskill,", circa 1930-circa 1936 (Folder 2.15)
  - "Kennerley Old Style,", circa 1930-circa 1940 (Folder 2.16)
  - "Kennerley Old Style,", circa 1930-circa 1943 (Folder 6.5)
  - "Lanston,", 1939 (Folder 2.17)
  - "Medieval,", 1930, 1939 (Folder 2.18)
  - "Modern,", circa 1918, 1934-circa 1940 (Folder 2.19)
  - Monograms, undated (Box 7)
  - "New Style,", 1949 (Folder 2.20)
  - "Old Style,", 1935, 1948, undated (Folder 2.21)
  - "Pabst Old Style,", circa 1938 (Folder 2.22)
  - "Record of Goudy Types,", undated (Folder 6.6)
  - "Saks,", 1934 (Folder 2.23)
  - "Saks,", undated (Folder 6.7)
  - A Specimen of Types Designed and Sold by Frederic W. Goudy, 1921 (Folder 14.1)
  - A Specimen Sheet Showing Almost All of the "Lost" Goudy Types, after 1936 (Folder 14.2)
  - "Text,", circa 1930-circa 1940 (Folder 2.24)
  - "Tory,", 1937 (Folder 2.25)
  - "Trajan,", 1940 (Folder 2.26)
  - "Truesdell,", 1939, 1941 (Folder 2.27)
  - "Village,", 1937, undated (Folder 2.28)
  - Unidentified type, 1932, 1943 (Folder 2.29)
- Series V. Broadsides
  - Village Press
    - Concerning Literary Style (Goethe), 1932; [3 copies] (Folder 14.3)
    - Excerpt from the Second Inaugural Address by Abraham Lincoln, circa 1932; [10 copies] (Folder 14.4-14.5)
    - Gettysburg Address, undated; [2 copies] (Folder 15.1)
    - Good Taste, Skill, 1932 (Folder 14.6)
    - A Specimen of Types Designed and Sold by Frederic W. Goudy, 1921 (Folder 14.1)
    - A Specimen Sheet Showing Almost All of the "Lost" Goudy Types, after 1936 (Folder 14.2)
  - Maverick Press
    - Assorted broadsides, undated (Folder 4.8)
  - Miscellaneous Broadsides
    - Development of Printing Types, undated (Folder 14.7)
    - Gutenberg's Invention, 1942 (Folder 15.1)
    - I am New York, circa 1939 (Folder 15.2)
    - Oath of Hippocrates, 1942 (Folder 15.3)
    - Assorted broadsides, circa 1922-circa 1940 (Folder 6.16)
- Series VI. Slides
  - Slides 1-200 (Box 10)
  - Slides 201-400 (Box 11)
  - Slides 401-500 (Box 12)
- Series VII. Book Covers, Bookplates, and Other Designs
  - Book covers (Folder 2.30)
  - Book jackets, brochures, etc., circa 1928-circa 1951 (Folder 2.31)
  - Book jackets designed by Goudy, 1918-1946 (Folder 6.8)
  - Bookplates, monograms, and title pages, circa 1910-circa 1945 (Folders 2.32-2.33)
  - Bookplates, monograms, and title pages, circa 1910-circa 1945 (Folder 6.9)
  - Books, programs, etc. designed by Goudy, circa 1903-circa 1950 (Folders 2.34-2.35)
  - Books, programs, etc. designed by Goudy, circa 1903-circa 1950 (Folder 6.10)
  - Exhibit catalog design, undated (Folder 6.11)
  - Miscellany News masthead, 1939 (Folder 2.36)
  - Monogram design (Folder 6.12)
  - Vassar College bookplates designed by Goudy and Borden bookplates, circa 1934-circa 1940 (Folder 2.37)
  - Vassar Cooperative Bookshop sign design, undated (Folder 15.5)
- Series VIII. Exhibits, Honors, and Tributes
  - "Le Chapeau Immortel,", 1928 (Folder 14.11)
  - Exhibits, 1933-1948 (Folder 2.38)
  - Exhibits at Vassar College, circa 1933-circa 1947 (Folder 2.39)
  - Goudy Dinner, 1929 (Folder 2.40)
  - Goudy at Vassar College, circa 1932-circa 1947 (Folder 3.1)
  - Honors, tributes, etc., 1930-1950, undated (Folders 3.2-3.4)
  - Honors and tributes, circa 1930-circa 1947 (Folder 6.13)
  - Songs, verses, etc. to Goudy, 1935-1938 (Folder 3.5)
  - Vassar College News Items, Exhibits, Birthday Parties, 1932-1944 (Folder 6.14)
  - Village Press 35th anniversary poster, 1938 (Folder 13.3)
- Series IX. Portraits and Memorabilia
  - Bas relief portrait of Frederic and Bertha Goudy, 1933 (Box 7)
  - Goudy at Vassar College pictures (Folder 3.6)
  - Master's degree award medal, 1901 (Box 7)
  - Pictures, Portraits, etc., circa 1935-circa 1948 (Folders 4.1-4.2)
  - Portrait of Frederic Goudy, 1928; [2 copies] (Folder 14.8)
  - Portrait of Frederic Goudy, 1932; [3 copies] (Folder 14.9)
  - Portrait of Frederic Goudy, 1942 (Folder 14.10)
  - Portraits of Frederic Goudy, 1935, undated (Folder 6.15)
  - Portraits of Frederic Goudy, circa 1930-1942 (Folder 13.4)
  - Portraits of Frederic and Bertha Goudy, 1932-1938 (Folder 13.5)
  - The story of the Goudy bas relief, 1937 (Folder 4.3)
  - Watermark Portrait, undated (Folder 4.4)
- Series X. Miscellaneous Files
  - Ars Typographica-announcements and prospectuses, circa 1918-1935 (Folder 4.5)
  - Bertha Goudy, circa 1935-circa 1938 (Folder 4.6)
  - Bruce Rogers' Lectern Bible, circa 1935-1948 (Folder 4.7)
  - Deepdene Estate, 1939-1948 (Folder 4.8)
  - Maverick Press, circa 1936-circa 1940 (Folder 4.9)
  - Miscellaneous printed material, circa 1922-circa 1940 (Folder 6.16)
  - Vassar College Village Press Collection, circa 1932-circa 1938; [Correspondence relating to collection] (Folder 5.1)
  - Village Press Bibliography, 1931-1945 (Folder 5.2)
  - Village Press Bibliography, 1947 (Folder 5.3)
  - Village Press Collections at Other Institutions, 1941-circa 1960 (Folder 5.4)